# Robert Hoelzle, PhD

#### **Data Scientist**

Data scientist and bioinformatician with 6 years' experience in bioinformatics programming, 11 years' experience in high paced R&D environment, and a life-long passion for problem solving. Proficient in Python, R, and Bash with many multivariate modelling and statistics techniques.

# **Experience**

### **Bioinformatics Research Fellow**

2016 – Present The University of Queensland Brisbane, Qld, AUS

- Published 4 peer-reviewed publications (+3 in review), including design of data analysis pipelines in <u>Shell</u>, <u>R</u>, and <u>Python</u> which integrate complex genomic, transcriptomic, and environmental datasets
- Slashed research group's processing time for genomic data by 60% through custom built <u>Python</u> bioinformatic programs for DNA data extraction
- Initiated and maintained consultancies with biotech industry stakeholders for microbiology solutions to soil carbon sequestration, copper bioleaching, and wastewater treatment projects
- Supervised eight research students, and mentored four research professionals, providing guidance for coding and data analysis in <u>Shell</u>, <u>R</u>, and <u>Python</u>

#### **Bioprocess Engineering PhD Student**

2012 – 2017 The University of Queensland Brisbane, Qld, AUS

- Published 3 peer-reviewed articles and 1 thesis, including design of data analysis pipelines in <u>Shell</u> and <u>R</u> which integrate complex genomic, proteomic, and environmental datasets
- Discovered and published novel bioplastic production method using custom bioreactors with self-designed environmental control systems in <u>C++</u>

### **Bioprocess Engineer**

2010 – 2012 Green Biologics Ltd Columbus, Ohio, USA

- Programmed environmental control systems in <u>C++</u> for pilot and demonstration scale biofuel reactors, resulting in a commercially operating biofuel plant
- Coordinated governmental lab certification by US National Renewable Energy Laboratory for pilot reactor research facility
- Supervised two research assistants for pilot and demonstration scale reactor development

## **Skills**

### Languages

<u>Python</u> (SKLearn, SciPy, Pandas, NumPy, Dash, IBM\_DB, FuzzyWuzzy)

<u>R</u> (Vegan, NbClust, RCy3, RStatix, mvabund, Ismeans, spaa, dplyr, tidyr, SpiecEasi)

Shell, T-SQL, SQLite, and C++

### **Modelling and Statistics**

Predictive modelling, generalized linear models, single/multiple linear and polynomial regression, advanced multivariate statistics, multivariate ordination, feature clustering, network analysis

#### **Cloud Infrastructure**

IBM Watson Studio, IBM DB2, Galaxy Australia

#### **Tools**

GitHub, Jupyter Notebook, R Studio

#### General

Creative problem solving, technical writing and communication, consulting, project management, budget management, team coordination

# **Education and Certificates**

- PhD (2017) The University of Queensland
   Chemical Engineering
- BSc w/ Honors (2010) The Ohio State University Chemical and Biomolecular Engineering
- Professional Cert (2022) IBM Data Science

# **Community Engagement**

- Joint Academic Microbiology Seminars (2018 Pr)
- March for Science Brisbane (2017)
- Engineers without Borders UQ (2015 2016)

### **Interests**

Rock Climbing Home Brewing
Ultimate Frisbee Escape Rooms
Photography Gardening